Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the National Caucus of Labor Committees PE.038
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the National Caucus of Labor Committees
1968-1980
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.038
1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
The National Caucus of Labor Committees (NCLC) Printed Ephemera Collection is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The NCLC, headed by Lyndon LaRouche, was purged from the Students for a Democratic Society in 1968 for supporting the New York Teachers Strike. Eventually the NCLC spawned the U.S. Labor Party, with LaRouche as their candidate for U.S. President, and the North American Unemployed and Welfare Rights Organization. The collection consists of printed ephemera put out by the organization nationally, largely fliers, fact sheets, press releases, and pamphlets. Also in the collection are materials from local NCLC chapters.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History Note
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Arrangement
The files are grouped in one series; folders are mainly arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
The National Caucus of Labor Committees (NCLC) is a political organization headed by Lyndon LaRouche. Originally a caucus within the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) called the Labor Committee, LaRouche and his followers were purged from SDS in 1968 for supporting the Albert Shankar led New York Teachers Strike. The NCLC later went on to attack those on the left in what is known as "Operation Mop Up" as well as to form their own rival organizations, including the National Unemployed and Welfare Rights Organization and the Revolutionary Youth Movement. The NCLC also founded the U.S. Labor Party which supported LaRouche's candidacy for U.S. President in 1976.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the National Caucus of Labor Committees consists of printed material generated at both the national and local chapter level, ranging in date from 1969-1978. There are numerous fliers outlining the organization's positions, largely in the form of attack campaigns on New York City and state politicians, the CIA, the Communist Party as well as other groups on the left. There are publicity materials for the NCLC's publications, The Campaigner and New Solidarity. Included are a number a pamphlets put out by the NCLC on topics such as Moscow and the popular front, socialism, labor and psychoanalysis, among other subjects. The collection also contains various printed material from local NCLC chapters.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
Pamphlets.; Right and left (Political science).; Fliers (printed matter); LaRouche, Lyndon H.; National Caucus of Labor Committees (U.S.)
- Amendments and Resolutions, undated (Box 1)
- Campaigner: Publicity Materials and Internal Discussion of (theoretical journal), 1970, undated (Box 1)
- Campaigner Publications, Inc., 1977-1978 (Box 1)
- Circular Letters and Memoranda, 1969-1977 (Box 1)
- CUNY, undated (Box 1)
- Conferences ("Strategy for Socialism"), 1969-1973, undated (Box 1)
- Editorials and Editorial Policy, 1970, undated (Box 1)
- Fact Sheets, 1974, undated (Box 1)
- Fliers, 1971-1972, undated (Box 1)
- Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) Files: Baltimore, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) Files: Philadelphia I, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) Files: Philadelphia II, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) Files: Seattle, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Fraser-Borgmann Defense Committee, undated (Box 1)
- Fundraising, 1974 (Box 1)
- Internal Discussion Bulletin, 1970 (Box 1)
- Internal Discussion Documents, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
- Labor Organizers Defense Fund, 1973 (Box 1)
- Literature Sales and Distribution, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
- Minutes, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
- National Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
- National Executive Committee, 1973, undated (Box 1)
- New Solidarity (newspaper), 1973-1977 (Box 1)
- News Service Bulletins, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
- News Service Bulletins I, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
- News Service Bulletins II, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
- "Operation Nuremburg", 1974 (Box 1)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1973 (Box 1)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1974-1983 (Box 1)
- Position Papers and Political Statements, 1970-1974, undated (Box 1)
- Press Releases, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- Press Reports to Locals and Publicity, 1974 (Box 1)
- Reports, 1970-1974, undated (Box 1)
- Revolutionary Youth Movement, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- "Statement of Founding Principles", circa 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Temple University, 1971 (Box 1)
- Vicki Gabriner Defense Fund, 1977 (Box 1)
- Ann Arbor Labor Committee, 1970 (Box 1)
- Baltimore Labor Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
- Boston Labor Committee, 1970, undated (Box 1)
- Chicago Labor Committee, 1973 (Box 1)
- Ithaca Labor Committee, 1970, undated (Box 1)
- New York Labor Committee I, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
- New York Labor Committee II, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
- Philadelphia Labor Committee (Fraser-Borgmann Defense Committee), 1969-1970 (Box 1)
- Rochester Labor Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
- Seattle Labor Committee, undated (Box 1)
- Stony Brook Labor Committee, undated (Box 1)
- Suffolk Labor Committee, 1970 (Box 1)
- Washington D.C. Labor Committee, circa 1970 (Box 1)